There's an important topic that we haven't talked about yet,
that is pretty important to most frameworks these days.
And that's state management, global state management for that.
Everything we've been doing right now has been encapsulated into
our various components.
So for example, one of the reasons why I have the restaurant page, you see here,
has all the data, and then I have this new restaurant form that is a subset,
and then being like sort of toggled back and forth,
is because at least prior to us talking about state management,
it's very tricky to pass data around our components like that.
So ideally, I would create another route,
and then that would share something in the global state.
That's what we would ideally like to see.
So what we're going to do is we're going to show you how to
basically do some state management with TypeScript
with the new library called Pina.
So if you haven't seen this cute little pineapple,
this is the mascot for our global state management.
And if you're wondering, like, oh, what about UX?
Well, UX is ultimately, I think, basically going to be
deprecated, and Pina is now the official state management solution.
So Pina, like few three, is built from the bottom up with TypeScript.
So it's designed to be really easy to use with it, actually.
So what we're going to do is we're going to assume that basically people,
they start first time that people are using Pina,
and then we're just going to sort of augment types as we did before.
So the thing about Pina, as far as I think state management in general,
is that in the past, you used to have to opt into modularity.
Yet to be like, OK, most people start out with this global store,
and then over time you broke that up into smaller pieces,
that then could be chunked when it loaded on a certain page.
You didn't load your entire global state on every single page.
And that was kind of like the progress.
But then I think at some point, people realize, wait,
I think we just want modular by default.
It was kind of silly to go that other direction to import everything at once.
So Pina follows that exact convention.
So first thing first is inside of our stores directory, currently empty.
Let me make sure I'm on the right branch, I am, great.
We're just going to create a new file, and I use Pascal case for naming the stores,
just because they're kind of like constants the way I see them.
So I'm going to do restaurant store.ts.
That's what I'm going to do.
And so, OK, now that we have this, what do we need to do?
Well, we're going to import a defined store helper from Pina.
So this is back to our composable discussion that we've been talking about,
where we have a lot of helper functions to help us do the view like things,
but in a declarative way that people would understand it.
So now that we have this defined store, what can we do?
Well, so we can define a constant, and what are we going to call it?
So it's a composable that's going to call upon the store.
So the use key word is going to be used here.
So use restaurant store is going to be what this is called.
And then we're going to call define store here.
So this kind of like define component, if you think about it.
Now you're defining a component, now you're defining a store.
And so what am I going to call it?
I'm just going to call it exactly what it's called, which is restaurant store.
So I usually map the, this is the idea of the store centrally,
and I map it directly to the file name.
So that's why I name it this way.
Casing is up to you, of course.
Now with that said, now we have an object that we pass that is going to consist of our stores.
So typically, in most state management, like redux and stuff,
you have your state, you have your getters, which are essentially your computer properties in view.
And then you have actions, and then you have mutations, right?
That's like your standard redux pattern.
But what I'm happy to tell you is that with pinia, mutations disappear.
No more boiler plate of like, call an action to then define a mutation,
to basically do the same thing.
That's all, we're taking care of that for you.
It's all good now.
So what this ultimately means is that to map it over to what we talked about before,
this is essentially our data object from options API.
This is our computed, and this is our methods.
Basically, what's happening?
So first thing first, let's go ahead and then have a list of data.
So to refactor this, I'm going to take the new restaurant page here,
or a restaurant page, and I'm going to take all of this out.
Okay, we're going to exnate that, and then actually I'll leave it at an empty array,
so that it doesn't yell at me, and then we're going to drop it inside of our restaurant store.
Okay, lots and lots of yelling, why is it yelling at me?
Use store function that would choose the store instance.
Oh, silly me, I forgot.
State, in case you're ever doing this, in the past, you could define your state just as an empty object,
but it's actually just like most reactivity system.
It needs to be a function that calls an object so that it's always getting its latest instance.
So once I turn this into the arrow function, that returns an object that contains the state,
there you go, now it is much happier with me.
And so again, something that type of kind of helped me out with this, because I would have just
barreled ahead, otherwise without that huge red, it's quickly like, okay, this looks much prettier.
So now that we have this, of course the question is, okay, how do we actually call the thing?
So let's go ahead and inside of our restaurant page.
We can go ahead now and import our composable use restaurant store.
And so what this is, again, what we're doing is we're basically setting it up.
So what I can do here is I can say cons restaurant store equals use restaurant store.
And so this now has a direct correlation to that store module that we're importing on this file.
And this is something that I personally have really come to like about using ping-pong,
you know versus like V-X where you just have this, this, that dollar sign store,
and you just have the sum things are where, then you have the name things.
This, I just name it whatever that makes sense to me, which is restaurant store.
Use restaurant store, I think most people can follow along this.
And then from here, believe it or not, let me log restaurant store for us to see what we're getting.
There you go, great.
Other way, all right, so now I've got a restaurant, nothing's here, but that makes sense.
You'll notice that inside of our proxy, we have basically everything, here, there's the list.
There's our list of all the things that we have inside of here, which means no longer
do you have to go like, oh store.state.this or whatever, the ergonomics are there so that we can
basically now say restaurant store.list. And so now if we refresh this and take a look, look,
there's our proxy with all our events, or sorry, all of our restaurants that we want.
So really, if we think about it, what we could do is we could just say that restaurant list,
we could just actually just do restaurant store.
That list, and then do do, cannot find any in our restaurant store.
I think that was a weird compiler bug. Okay, and so again, what's nice though, is that now that you're
actually in this like proxy, reactive like environment, all the values actually just disappear.
That's what your text is fine. So restaurant list.filter, this is great, but it's yelling at us
why, because right now we don't have any types. This actually does make sense.
Because again, we've defined it, we've used it, but how do we tell Pinia that we have a list of
restaurants? Well, it's as they just like we did before. I would just call it state shape, and then I'm
going to say that hey, the list is a list of restaurants in a ray. And then when the object is
returned, what am I expecting? State shape. So now that I have that, when I go back to restaurant
page, you'll notice all the squiggly lines have disappeared, and more importantly, I don't need value anymore.
And that's it. I have now brought everything in. And so let's continue on this, let's continue on
this refactor as well. So we have the ability to see the list and all that stuff. So let's go ahead,
and now let's take a look at some getters, right? What are some common getters that we have? Well,
we can clean this up quite a bit where we actually know I think about it. We don't really need this,
let's see. We don't need a number of restaurants to live inside of this file. This is something
that makes sense to live inside of the store. So let's move it. So we're going to go ahead and take
that out. Actually, let me just comment it out so I don't forget that I need to do that. And then
inside of here, we can say a number of restaurants, right? And then this is where I have to recall
real quick. Let's just pull up the docs. Just to make sure I do this right.
Because this is a discussion that's worth having real quick. Okay.
So something, again, that used to happen in the past, is that whenever you would reference the
state, you had to use it in a normal function. You couldn't use the arrow function because you're
lying on this. But again, in an effort to be a little bit more modular, as you can see,
getters now can actually take an arrow function where they automatically get past the state
as the first parameter. So now that we know that, we can basically then say, all right, well,
this takes an argument of state. And what is it going to do? It's going to return.
Okay, for now, this is actually, I know why this is going to be a problem, but it's fine.
We're just going to practice this. State.list.length. That's it. And then if you want to annotate
it, that's totally fine. We just add the number onto the annotation for the arrow function description.
Okay, that's taking care of. And so this will be a little bit tricky later, but it's fine.
We'll just crack on. And then here's the thing, things like deleting a restaurant, adding a restaurant.
How do we do this? Well, these are things that really belong inside once again the store.
This should be like something that we actually call an action for. So how does that look like?
Well, in this particular case, again, just a matchup with documentation. You'll see that it
does something a little bit differently now, is that because when you use this syntax, just like I
was mentioning, it actually needs to get the whole instance of the store now. We no longer can just
get the state. And though this is kind of tricky when it comes to auto-completion and stuff,
but especially because of things like asynchronous and that kind of thing. Typically when you're running
actions, you're not going to use an arrow function. That's just general best practice. But on the
upside, what this means, though, is that Eduardo and the team who work on PINIA have made the
this thing actually still have auto-complete as you would expect when it comes to typing and that
kind of stuff. So what we would do here is we would basically say, okay, so we have here,
that is going to get the payload, and the payload is still going to be a restaurant. That's fine.
But then we can say this.list.push payload. We're not going to worry about that right now,
and then when we had delete restaurant, similarly, we'll get a payload of restaurant.
And then this.list equals this.list.list.filter restaurant, great, we'll just type that.
And then there you go. So 1, 2, 3. So now we need to actually make sure we call all of these things
inside of our page. So I'm going to go ahead and let me just, I can just see the hide form is still
something that's important. So this is where, for example, now, okay. So we have inside of here,
at restaurant, so how do we do this? So inside of at restaurant, you'll notice that is being
called right here, and we know that we're getting the payload. So what we're going to do is when
it's still called this at restaurant, that's totally fine. But rather than actually modifying
it directly here, all we need to do is call restaurant store.at restaurant, and then drop in the payload.
But boom, const, save. Why is it saying can't find name at restaurant? Okay, I think we're
okay now. That was super weird. Yep, no errors being yelled at, great. Okay, so we can test this
out real quick, basically by going into our app, refresh much better. Okay, so now when we hit new,
and we do test test.com, I forgot I have to sign it. There we go. Now when we create it,
there we go. It is actually appearing as expected. And so again, I could walk through the rest of this,
but I think the most important thing I want to show you here with the global store is that it really
doesn't look that different from a regular component instance. Besides explicit keywords,
like state is the data that you're going to be pulling from. Getters is computed,
and then actions like this could easily be mapped to what we learned earlier today as far as
like methods computed and state and then state shape, data data shape. I think that's what's
important to realize with in this journey with view and high script is that the goal is really
not to make you learn something brand new in terms of syntax. It should feel very familiar
as you're moving from thing to thing.